Guide to the New York State Ornithological Association (NYSOA) records
New York State Ornithological Association (NYSOA) records.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
New York State Ornithological Association, 1946-2013.
4860
New York State Ornithological Association.
6.9 cubic feet
Minutes of meetings, membership rosters, announcements, programs of annual meetings, photographs and news clippings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Materials relating to the organization's history and ongoing business, including minutes of meetings, membership rosters, announcements, and programs of annual meetings, photographs, news clippings, correspondence and special projects such as the New York State Avian Records Committee, and the New York State Bird Book Committee.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
From its first organizational meeting in Rochester in 1946, the Federation of New York State Bird Clubs served as a mechanism for birders in the state to share their ideas and experiences and to promote research, education, and conservation. The Federation numbered more than forty bird clubs in 1992, with a combined membership of over twenty thousand birders. It is governed by a council of delegates representing those clubs. Individual memberships are also accepted. Many 20th century ornithologists and prominent birders in New York State have been associated with the Federation, serving as club officers and contributing to "The Kingbird" such as Peter Paul Kellogg, Arthur A. Allen, Winston Brockner, Eugene Eisenmann, and Sally Hoyt Spofford. The name of the Federation of New York State Bird Clubs was changed to the New York State Ornithological Association (NYSOA) at a vote of its Council of Delegates meeting on November 1, 2003.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Materials relating to the organization's history and ongoing business, including minutes of meetings, membership rosters, announcements, and programs of annual meetings, photographs, news clippings, "New York Birders" from 1971, "The Kingbird" from 1950, correspondence and special projects such as the New York State Avian Records Committee, and the New York State Bird Book Committee. The bulk of the material was collected by Federation co-founder Dr. Gordon Meade, until his death in 1990, with correspondence of Dr. Foster Gambrell contributed by Charles A. Rouse of the Eaton Birding Society. Material collected by Mary Ann Sunderlin, who held numerous executive positions in the Federation: Corresponding Secretary, Recording Secretary, and Vice President, was donated to the Federation after her death in 1992. The complete set of "New York Birders," 1871-1993 was collected by Stanley Lincoln, President of the Federation from 1991-1993.
Publications include A Summary of the Hamlin Beach lakewatch fall and winter waterbird migration data, 1993-1999 by Brett Ewald and Dominic F. Sherony, 2001; Bull's Birds of New York State, Emanuel Levine, edition, 1998; the Atlas of Breeding Birds in New York State, edited by Robert F. Andrle and Janet R. Carroll, 1988; and Checklists of the Birds of New York State, 1989, 1991, 1996, 1999 -, Kingbird. Also a seal of the organization.
Andrlé, Robert F.; Brockner, Winston William; Carroll, Janet R.; Eaton Birding Society.; Eisenmann, Eugene, 1906-; Federation of New York State Bird Clubs..; Gambrell, Foster L.; Kellogg, Peter Paul, 1899-; Levine, Emmanuel; Lincoln, Stanley; Meade, Gordon M., 1907-1990; New York State Avian Records Committee.; Federation of New York State Bird Clubs.; New York State Bird Book Committee.; New York State Young Birders Club..; Rouse, Charles A.; Sherony, Dominic; Spofford, Sally Hoyt; Sunderlin, Mary Ann; Aviculture--New York (State); Birds--Societies, etc.; Ornithology--Study and teaching--New York (State)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
- Organization
  - Origins of the Federation (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Documents of Incorporation and other official federal and state papers, 1956-1969 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Name change (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - By-Laws
    - Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1959-1998 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Minutes of the Executive Committee and Related Documents – Board of Directors, 1995-
    - Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 33-35)
    - 1979-2008 (Box 7, Folder 41-46)
    - February 7, 2009 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - April 4, 2009 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - November 21, 2009 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - February 20, 2010 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - April 10, 2010 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - July 17, 2010 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - November 20, 2010 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - February 5, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - April 2, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - July 9, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - November 5, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - February 4, 2012 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - April 21, 2012 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - July 14, 2012 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - November 3, 2012 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - February 9, 2013 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - April 6, 2013 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - July 13, 2013 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - November 16, 2013 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - President's file
    - President's file, Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Arranged and collected by Stanley R. Lincoln...to be passed on to succeeding presidents
    - President's file, 1996-2001 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Items removed from President's File Briefcase, 1995-
      - President's file part 1, ca. 1998-2006 (Box 8, Folder 44)
        Contains 1. Annual meeting official notification letter; 2. By-Laws; 3. Certificate of Incorporation; 4. Council of delegates meetings: recent agendas; 5. Board of Directors contact list; 6. Federal tax exemption number/certificate; 7. Financial report, budget, historical comparisons; 8. History, annual meetings - location, host clubs, officers, editors, minuts of meetings of delegates, awards, purpose and receipients, NYSARAC reports ref/former members, origins of the federation and what happened then 1947-1988.
      - President's file part 2, ca. 1998-2006 (Box 8, Folder 45)
        Contains 9. Member clubs list, delegates authorized, roster of club officers; 10. Membership report; 11. New York birders annual schedule; 12. New York State sales tax exemption umber/form; 13. NYSARC rules, current members/terms; 14. Policies, guidelines, advisory committee, affiliations, club grants, proposal concerning membership committees duties; 15. Resolutions adopted by council of delegates, 1991-92, 1988.
      - President's file miscellaneous, ca. 2002 (Box 8, Folder 46)
        Correspondence.
      - Pouch containing the official seal paper embossing stamp (Box 8)
  - Financial Reports and Related Documents
    - Through 1979; 1980- (Box 7, Folder 37-40)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Annual Meetings, Brochures and Announcements
    - Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1948-1958 (Box 7, Folder 65-75)
    - 1960 (Box 7, Folder 76)
    - 1968- (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1963-1979 (Box 7, Folder 77-93)
    - 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 94-96)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 97-99)
    - 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
    - 1997-2008 (Box 1, Folder 11-22)
  - Rosters
    - Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1949-2003 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Brochures and Promotional Materials (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brochures and Promotional Materials (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Brochures and Promotional Materials (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Committees
  - Administrative, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Bibliography, 1953-1999 (Box 8, Folder 34-35)
  - Membership
    Reports and correspondence
    - Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Undated (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - 1948-1999 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - 1950-2003 (Reports) (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - New York State Avian Records Committee (NYSARC), 1938-1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - State Bird Book Committee, 1947-1977 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - State Bird Book Committee, 1947-1977 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Conservation
    - Bulletins (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Issues 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1950s (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1970s (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1980s (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, Undated (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - New York State Avian Records Committee
    - Files, 1972-2000 (Box 11, Folder 27)
- Special Projects
  - Hamlin Beach Lakewatch Migration Data, 1993-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Resident Bird Survey, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Spring Migration Survey, 1974-1980 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - New York State Young Birders Club (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - NYS Young Birders Club (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Waterfowl Counts, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Forest Resources Planning Programs, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Project Birdwatch, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Chesapeake Bay Program, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Field trips
    - Adirondacks, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Adirondacks, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Adirondacks, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Pelagic, 1974-1981 (Box 11, Folder 36)
- Publications
  - 2nd Atlas of Breeding birds, documents, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 40)
  - Conservation Now! (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Checklist of the Birds of New York State
    - Checklists
      - Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - 1952 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - 2009-2011 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - 2013-2014 (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1991 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Kingbird
    - Vol. 1-6, 1950-1957 (Box 1)
    - Vol. 7-24, 1957-1974 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 25-27, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Vol. 28-29, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 30-35, 1980-1985 (Box 1)
    - Vol. 36-43, 1986-1993 (Box 2)
    - Vol. 44-46, 1994-1996 (Box 4)
    - Vol. 47-51, 1997-2001 (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
    - Vol. 51-58, 2001-2008 (Box 6)
    - Vol. 59, No. 1, March 2009 (Box 6)
    - Vol. 59, No. 2-4, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Vol. 60, 2010 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Vol. 61, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Vol. 62 no.1-4, 2012 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Vol. 63 no.1-3, 2013 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Ten Year Index, Vol. 1-20, 1950-1970 (Box 2)
    - Ten Year Index, Vol. 31-40, 1981-1990 (Box 4)
    - Kingbird Regional Boundaries, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1954-2010 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - New York Birders
    - Vol. 1-22, 1972-1993 (Box 2, Folder 29-32)
    - Vol. 23-25, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 26-37, 1997-2008 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Vol. 38, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Vol. 39, 2010 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Vol. 40, 2011 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Vol. 41, no. 1-4, 2012 (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - Vol. 42, no. 1-4, 2013 (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1994 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Books
    - Bull's Birds of New York State (Box 5)
    - Bull's Birds of New York State, correspondence, 1989-1997 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Atlas of Breeding Birds in New York State, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Atlas of Breeding Birds in New York State, documents, 1979-1984 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Second Atlas of Breeding Birds in New York State, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Second Atlas of Breeding Birds in New York State, documents
      - 1998 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - 2000-2005 (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Letter of agreement, July 31, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 28)
      - Logo (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - Steering committee (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - Regional Coordinators (Box 7, Folder 32)
      - Volunteers (Box 7, Folder 33)
      - Publication (Box 7, Folder 34)
      - DEC Documents (Box 7, Folder 35)
      - Recommendations (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Where to Find Birds in New York State, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Website
    - Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 11, Folder 41)
- Awards
  - Lillian C. Stoner Award, 1977-2002 (Box 7, Folder 1-27)
  - Elon Howard Eaton Memorial Award, 1965-1998 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Elon Howard Eaton Memorial Award, 1965-1998 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1975-1999 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Officers Correspondence and Documents
  - William Winston Brockner, 1946-1999 (Box 6, Folder 3-12)
    President, 1950-51
  - Allen Benton, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    President, 1966-1967
    Scope and Contents note
    Monthly newsletter to executive committee
  - Kenneth D. Niven, 1971-1973 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    President 1971-1972
  - Richard Sloss
    President 1975-76
    - Audubon Council (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Current and Pending (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Copies of General Correspondence (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Officers and Committees (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Finances (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Membership (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - Membership Brochure (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Kingbird (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - New York Birders (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Birding Consultants (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Area Representatives (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Projects and Ideas (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - State Bird Societies (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - New Club Prospects (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Education (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Falconry (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Lona Coates, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    Recording secretary 1975-1975
  - Stephen B. Dempsey, 1971-1977 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    President 1977-1978; Treasurer 1971-1976
  - Chad E. Covey (Box 3, Folder 5)
    President 1989-1991
  - Stanley R. Lincoln, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Mary Ann Sunderlin, 1969-1991 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    Vice-president, 1971-71, 1975-1976; Recording secretary, 1969-1970; Corresponding secretary 1987-1991; Co-editor of New York Birders, 1972-1978
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Individuals' Papers
  - Foster Gambrell (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Gordon M. Meade, M.D., 1948-1985 (Box 8, Folder 11-16)
    Federation of New York State Bird Clubs founder
  - Robert L. Miller, re: Gordon M. Meade (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - News Clippings
    - Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 1946-1987 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Photographs
    - Federation Activities photograph album (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Federation Activities (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Federation Activities (Box 8)
    - Federation Activities (Box 8, Folder 9-10)
    - Golden Anniversary Meeting album (Box 8)
    - 1st Annual meeting, November 13-14, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 8th Annual meeting, May 28-29, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Annual Meetings Photos, undated; CD-621 (Box 9)
  - Biographies, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Speakers Bureau, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - NYSOA notebook, 1971-1976 (Box 8, Folder 41-42)